Guide to the Annie Burr Lewis and Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Photographs
The Lewis Walpole Library
Annie Burr Lewis and Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Photographs
1859-1979
1900-1959
LWL MSS 22
The Lewis Walpole Library
37.1
36 boxes + 1 broadside + 1 roll
The Annie Burr Lewis and Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Photograph Collection consists of prints, negatives, transparencies, slides, and tintypes that provide visual documentation of the lives, family, friends, and activities of Wilmarth and Annie Burr Lewis. The images range from formal portraits by noted artists such Arnold Genthe and Yousuf Karsh, to hundreds of snapshots taken by friends and family, and by Annie Lewis herself. The material spans a full century in date, from a group of tintypes to photographs of family members through snapshots taken of Wilmarth Lewis before his death in 1979, but most of the images date from the first half of the twentieth century and cover the couple's childhoods through the death of Annie Lewis in 1959.
Lewis, Annie Burr Auchincloss, 1902-1959
Bell, Curtis
Chamberlain, Samuel, 1895-1975
Covell, William King, 1904-1975
Fullerton, Henry Suydam, 1916-2001
Genthe, Arnold, 1869-1942
Hewitt, Mattie Edwards, 1869-1956
Karsh, Yousuf, 1908-2002
Stoller, Ezra
Alman & Co
Runnels & Stateler
W. F. Miller & Co
Underwood & Underwood
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis (Yale 1918), 1979.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis, 1895-1979. II. Annie Burr Lewis, 1903-1959. III. Wilmarth and Annie Burr Lewis, 1927-1958. IV. Family and Friends, 1859-1975. V. Places, 1860-1978. VI. Unsorted and Unidentified Images, 1900-1979.
Annie Burr Lewis (1902-1959)
Annie Burr Auchincloss Lewis was born in Newport, Rhode Island, on July 22, 1902, the daughter of Emma Jennings Auchincloss and Hugh Dudley Auchincloss. She attended Miss Porter's School in Farmington, Connecticut, and married Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis in New York in 1928. She died in Hartford, Connecticut, on May 9, 1959.
Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis (1895-1979)
Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis was born in Alameda, California, on November 14, 1895, the son of Miranda Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis and Azro Nathaniel Lewis. He attended the Thacher School in Ojai, California, and Yale University (Class of 1918). He met Annie Burr Auchincloss in Farmington, Connecticut, in 1923, and the couple were married in 1928. Together they spent three decades building a collection of books, prints, paintings, manuscripts, and decorative arts related to Horace Walpole, his circle, and his time, and formed a research library at their home in Farmington. Lewis died in Hartford on October 7, 1979; he left his home and collections to Yale University by bequest.
Related Materials
Associated Material: Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20). The Lewis Walpole Library.
Associated Material: Annie Burr Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 21). The Lewis Walpole Library.
Scope and Contents
The Annie Burr Lewis and Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Photographs consists of prints, negatives, transparencies, slides, and tintypes that provide visual documentation of the couple's lives, family, friends, and activities. The images range from formal portraits by noted artists such Arnold Genthe and Yousuf Karsh, to hundreds of snapshots taken by friends and family. A good portion of the photographs were taken by Annie Lewis herself. She was an avid photographer and unfortunately, because she was behind the lens, images of her form only a small part of the collection—a rare photo of her posing with her camera in San Francisco in March 1939 can be found in the album in Box 31. Fortunately, however, Annie Lewis was mindful about captioning photographs, especially in the eleven albums she composed, and it is because of her careful work that many of the faces and places in the couple's picture collection can be identified today. She mounted prints in standard commercially available albums, but also created albums by affixing prints to pages in leather-bound volumes purchased as blank books or that formerly held Walpoliana collected by the couple.
The images span a full century in date, from a group of tintypes to photographs of family members through snapshots taken of Wilmarth Lewis before his death in 1979, though most are from the first half of the twentieth century and cover the couple's childhoods through the death of Annie Lewis in 1959. Both brought into their marriage, or later inherited, a variety of family photographs. Wilmarth Lewis, in particular, was the recipient of pictures and genealogical material owned by his brothers in California, which had been sent east by Charles, his only surviving sibling, prior to his death in 1969. The earliest item in the collection is not a photograph but the case that once held a daguerreotype or ambrotype of Annie Lewis's father Hugh Dudley Auchincloss (1858-1913) and his mother Elizabeth Buck Auchincloss, taken in 1859; the image itself is unlocated.
While much of the material in the collection is in black and white, there are many color photographs present. Notable are the approximately 250 sheet film transparencies and more than 600 slides taken by Annie Lewis, and from which she regularly had color prints made by the Pavelle laboratory in New York. Another remarkable group of color images exists in the two sets of stereo slides in the collection, which document the interiors of the Lewises' homes, the Major General Solomon Cowles House (1784) in Farmington, Connecticut, and the Jahleel Brenton farmhouse (1720) at Hammersmith Farm in Newport, Rhode Island. They are accompanied by a Realist Red Button stereo slide viewer which provides that format's intended three-dimensional effect.
Architect-designed houses -- Connecticut; Dwellings -- Connecticut -- Farmington; Dwellings -- Rhode Island -- Newport; Photographers; Farmington (Conn.); Newport (R.I.); Aerial photographs; Black-and-white negatives; Black-and-white photographs; Color negatives; Color photographs; Color slides; Color transparencies; Glass plate negatives; Group portraits; Platinum prints; Studio portraits; Tintypes (prints); Photograph albums; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979; Bell, Curtis; Chamberlain, Samuel, 1895-1975; Covell, William King, 1904-1975; Fullerton, Henry Suydam, 1916-2001; Genthe, Arnold, 1869-1942; Hewitt, Mattie Edwards, 1869-1956; Jennings, Annie Burr, 1855-1939; Karsh, Yousuf, 1908-2002; Lewis, Annie Burr Auchincloss, 1902-1959; Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon), 1895-1979; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Rand, Ellen Emmet, 1875-1941; Stoller, Ezra; Alman & Co; Runnels & Stateler; W. F. Miller & Co; Underwood & Underwood; Miss Porter's School (Farmington, Conn.)
- Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis, 1895–1979; Series I; 5.71; 6 boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds portraits of Wilmarth Lewis made throughout his life, as well as photographs that document his involvement with various organizations, institutions, and groups. The first subseries, Portraits, contains images of Lewis photographed alone, by commercial studios or informally in snapshots by friends and family. The Activities subseries shows Lewis at dedications, conferences, dinners, and events, as well as receiving awards. Five folders at the end of the series contain snapshot photographs of him relaxing with friends and family, playing croquet, and posing with his beloved dogs.
  Many additional photographs of Lewis appear in Annie Lewis's photograph albums in Series II, Boxes 29-32.
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Portraits and Activities, and arranged chronologically thereunder.
  - Portraits
    - As an infant, 1895–1897 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - As a toddler, 1897–1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Childhood, 1900–1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Album pages with childhood photographs, 1896–1910 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 1)
      Four pages from an unidentified album with portraits and snapshot photographs of Lewis and family members.
    - Thacher School and Yale College, 1910–1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - United States Army, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Arnold Genthe sitting, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Arnold Genthe sitting, 1929 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    - Candid and formal portraits, 1930–1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - At office desk, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - At office desk, 1939 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 2)
      Date established by inscription on mat.
    - Office of Strategic Services, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - In East Library and New Library, at home in Farmington, Connecticut, 1944 September (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 3)
      Two photographs by Nina Leen - Pix, for Life magazine.
    - Yousuf Karsh sitting, 1944 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      The Karsh studio files record Lewis's visit as sitting no. 9387, on November 24, 1944. The collection holds eleven prints featuring six different poses.
    - Yousuf Karsh sitting, 1944 November 24 (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 4-6)
      Additional copies of prints housed in Karsh studio enclosures.
    - Candid and formal portraits, 1950–1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Candid and formal portraits, 1960–1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - At office desk, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Candid and formal portraits, 1970–1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bruce Anderson sitting, University of Melbourne, 1972 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Meyers Studio silhouette, 1979 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Passport photographs, 1928-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Ellen Emmet Rand portrait, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Photograph by Meyers Studio of 1931 oil portrait of Lewis, which he left by bequest to the National Portrait Gallery in Washington, D.C. (NPG.80.8).
  - Activities
    - At Thacher School, 1911-1912, undated (Box 21 (Oversize), Folder 7-8)
    - At Thacher School, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - On trips with friends, 1914–1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - At Yale College
      - Group portraits, circa 1918 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 1)
        One of Scroll and Key members, and one unidentified group.
      - Group portrait, circa 1918 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 2)
        An unidentified group (Phi Beta Kappa?)
    - In weddings of unidentified friends, circa 1918-1925 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    - At Thacher School, 1946–1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - At Thacher School, 1978 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 3)
    - At Smith College for eighteenth-century symposium, 1947 January (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - In Australia, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - At Carl Rollins birthday dinner, 1956 January (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - At Yale University Art Gallery alumni pictures exhibition, 1956 May (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - At Mory's, receiving Mory's Cup, 1957 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    - At University College, Dublin, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - At Wedgwood International Seminar, Boston, 1958 April 19 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - With Yale Corporation, 1958–1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      See also Annie Lewis's photo album in Box 31.
    - At Yale Class of 1918 reunions, 1958, 1963, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - At Yale Class of 1918 reunions, 1958 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 5)
    - At Bucknell University, 1958 September (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - At University of Delaware, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - At Yale University Press events, 1961–1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - At Yale for Morse and Stiles colleges dedication, 1962 December 7 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - At Smithsonian Institution art commission meetings, 1963, 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - At Yale for Beinecke Library opening, 1963 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - At Yale for Kingman Brewster inauguration, 1964 April 11 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - At Miss Porter's School, 1964 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - At Monday Evening Club, 1965–1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - At Yale Medal ceremony and Yale Commencement, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Biographical / Historical
      Lewis received the Yale Medal on February 20th, and was awarded an Honorary Doctor of Laws on June 14th.
    - With Yale University Library staff at Farmington, 1965 May 22 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - At Blanche Knopf award dinner, 1966 October 11 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - At festschrift event, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - At Strawberry Hill, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - At University of San Francisco for Gleeson Library Associates meeting, 1969 March 9 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - At Deerfield, 1970 May (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - At University of Hartford for Mortensen Library dedication, 1971 October 3 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - At Trinity College, Hartford, 1973 October 29 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - At National Portrait Gallery, Washington, D.C., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - At Yale University Library Associates event, 1974 November (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - At Hobart College, 1976 May (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - At Farmington Bicentennial Celebration, 1976 July 4 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - With friends and family, 1931–1976 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      Some photographs have names and dates inscribed on verso but most do not. Also filed here are images of Lewis at Yale commencements.
    - Playing croquet with friends, 1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - With dogs, 1934–1959 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - With dog, 1961 August 8 (Box 22 (Oversize), Folder 6)
      Informal portrait in The Castle at Newport, by "Miss Sirkis."
- Annie Burr Lewis, 1903–1959; Series II; 13.73; 13 boxes
  The series holds images of Annie Lewis photographed alone and in activities with friends and family. Her formal portraits start in infancy with images by the Alman & Co. studio, and continue with nationally prominent artists Curtis Bell and Arnold Genthe, and other professional studios in New York and Hartford. Also present in the Portraits subseries is a curiosity: a glass plate negative and two prints of a portrait painted by Ellen Emmet Rand which is similar to—but is not—the painting owned by the Lewises and now in the Lewis Walpole Library.
  Compared with images of Wilmarth Lewis and friends in the other series, there are many fewer candid photographs of Annie Lewis engaged in activities, primarily because she was usually the one behind the camera.
  As the eleven photograph albums in the Lewises' photograph collection were created by Annie Lewis, they are filed here although they hold images of both Lewises and their family and friends. Their contents were generally described at the item level for ease of access to images by location, event, or date. Many of the unidentified photographs in Series VI may be identified by checking images against those in the albums.
  Series II is organized into three subseries: Portraits, Activities, and Albums, and arranged chronologically thereunder.
  - Portraits
    - Negatives, 1903–1905 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
      Three glass plate negatives with two images on each plate; they likely originated at the Alman & Co. studio in New York, and were used to make the series of platinum prints that are stamped on verso "Lee E. Paulmann Photographic Laboratories, Bristol, Conn."
    - Negatives, undated
    - As an infant, 1903, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - As an infant, undated (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 3)
      Single sheet with portrait vignettes.
    - As a toddler, 1904–1905 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - As a youth, 1907–1908 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
      Folder 4 holds two framed photographs: a portrait in a carved ivory frame, and in a mosaic frame, a candid photo of her with a small pig.
    - As a youth, 1907–1908 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    - As a youth, 1907–1908 (Box 20 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    - As a teenager, 1912, circa 1914 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - As a teenager, 1912, circa 1914 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    - Curtis Bell sittings, 1916, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Wedding portraits, 1928 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 3-6)
      Images include one full-length pose, two seated poses, and a group portrait with bridesmaids; one of the latter images was annotated by Annie Lewis to identify her attendants. The setting is the home of her mother, Emma Jennings Auchincloss, at 33 East 67th Street in New York, where the wedding took place. The photographer is unidentified.
    - Arnold Genthe sitting, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Arnold Genthe sitting, 1929 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 7)
    - At Newport, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - At Christmas, 1930 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 8)
    - John Haley sitting, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      This portrait was used in publicity for the Women's Organization for National Prohibition Reform; also present is a three-quarter pose.
    - John Haley sitting, 1932 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 9-10)
    - American Red Cross portraits and photographs, circa 1942 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Other studio portraits, circa 1916-1930 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Passport photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - In Cowles House garden with George Washington dumb stove, 1958 December (Box 5, Folder 13)
      This image was so favored by Wilmarth Lewis that he reproduced it in his autobiography One Man's Education. In the text he describes Annie Lewis setting up the camera so he could snap the photograph himself.
    - In Cowles House garden with George Washington dumb stove, 1958 December (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 11)
    - Other images, 1918–1959 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Gravestone, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Portrait by Ellen Emmet Rand
      - Prints, circa 1935 (Box 5, Folder 16)
        Two photographs of a painted portrait of Annie Lewis which is a variant of the portrait owned by the library. The painting's history and location are unknown.
      - Negative, circa 1935 (Box 24 (Oversize))
        One glass plate negative from which the above photographic prints were made.
      - Negative box, circa 1936 (Box 25 (Oversize))
        A wooden box in which the glass plate negative was housed prior to 2016. The lid was inscribed in black crayon: "Glass Negative of Mrs Lewises Portrait"; inside is a folded section of the New York Times from April 26, 1936, which had served as padding for the plate.
  - Activities
    - As a child, with friends and pets, and in travels, circa 1904-1912 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - As a child, in travels, 1913 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      Album pages with scenes in Newport, Fairfield, Scotland, and St. Augustine, Florida, with images of Annie Auchincloss and pets.
    - Miss Porter's School theatricals and group photographs, 1917–1919 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      Additional photographs of theatricals can be found in the Miss Porter's School photograph album (Box 26).
    - As an adult, with friends and family, 1918–1954 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Caroline Parker's bridesmaids, 1922 July (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 12)
      A group portrait of attendants at the wedding of Caroline Parker to Staunton Williams in Cooperstown, New York, in July 1922. Annie Lewis labelled the print with names of some of the women who were friends from Miss Porter's School. She is not in the photograph, but Caroline Williams was an attendant in the Auchincloss-Lewis wedding in 1928.
    - At Christmas costume dinners, 1926–1927 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      Portraits and group portraits by Underwood & Underwood of Auchincloss and Jennings family members attending holiday dinners at the New York home of Annie Burr Jennings.
    - At Christmas costume dinners, circa 1925-1929 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 13)
    - In costume, circa 1930 (Box 23 (Oversize), Folder 14)
      Annie Lewis in a Spanish or Mexican costume worn at the 1926 Jennings Christmas dinner, posing with an unidentified man in formal wear; it is accompanied by a portrait, taken in the same location, of Azro Lewis, who is also dressed in Spanish or Mexican costume.
  - Albums
    Annie Lewis kept a series of albums, with photographs arranged sequentially from 1896 through 1958, which document her travels and activities. Favorite places visited regularly include her two homes in Farmington and Newport; those of her relatives in Fairfield, Connecticut, and Jekyll Island, Georgia; and friends in Salisbury, Connecticut (Whitridge) and Conway, Massachusetts (MacLeish).
    Another album, the Cowles House guest register, titled A Book of Hospitalities and a Record of Guests, is in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20), Box 291. It holds a chronology of snapshots of friends and family who came to stay with the Lewises in Farmington and were photographed (likely by Annie Lewis) during their visit; the small-scale prints were then glued to the pages where the guests' signatures appeared.
    - Family and friends album, 1896–1914 (Box 26 (Oversize))
      The album opens with studio portraits of Esther, Hugh, and Annie Auchincloss (1896-circa 1903), and thereafter holds photographs of Annie's friends and views in France, Newport, Florida, Farmington, Fairfield, and at Mount Vernon (1910-1914). Laid in at the end of the album are circa 1910 photographs of three historic buildings in Annapolis, Maryland: the Peggy Stewart house, the Richard Carvel house, and the Chase-Lloyd house.
    - Travel album, 1911 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      The album contains photographs taken at sea, in Egypt, France, Newport, Fairfield, Florida, and Farmington.
    - "Summer" album, 1915–1916 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      The album contains photographs taken on a family trip to the west coast, including scenes in Niagara Falls, Minnesota, Washington, British Columbia, and Alberta (June-July 1915); also with friends and family at Newport, Fairfield, and New Haven (August-October 1915), White Sulphur Springs, West Virginia (March 1916), Newport (June-September 1916), and Fairfield (October-November 1916).
    - Travel frame with five photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
      A folding leather travel frame, gold-stamped with "ABA" monogram and "Made in France," accompanied by five photographs of friends formerly held within. The photographs are uncaptioned and unidentified.
    - Miss Porter's School album, 1917–1919 (Box 27 (Oversize))
      The album opens with photographs of friends taken in Chester, New Hampshire, at New Year's 1917; the remainder of the album contains images of friends at beaches and at Miss Porter's School; most are not identified except for pages inscribed "Farmington Winter Term 1919" and "Spring Term 1919." There are two photographs of the theatrical production of Monsieur Beaucaire with Annie Auchincloss in the title role, and one group photograph of Miss Porter students.
    - Farmington album, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      The album contains photographs taken in Farmington and at Miss Porter's School.
    - Travel album, 1921–1925 (Box 28 (Oversize))
      The album contains snapshot photographs taken in Italy (March-April 1921), Spain (1922), England (1923), France, Switzerland, Italy, and Fairfield (1924), North Africa (January 1925), and Connecticut and Newport (1925). Also in the album is a watercolor view of the Bridge of Sighs in Venice, signed at lower right "G Marini." The album was likely purchased by the Auchinclosses in Italy in 1921 and contains a number of commercial photographs published by Italian and Spanish firms.
    - Travel album, 1928–1932 (Box 29 (Oversize))